<appendix id="changelog"><title>Revision History</title>
    <!--################################################################-->
    <section id="cl-032"><title>Version 0.3.2</title>
	<subtitle>July 08, 2003</subtitle>

	<para>
	    Version 0.3.2 is a bug fix release.
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Fixed a bug where socket file descriptors could be leaked. Thanks goes to Steve Bannister.
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Fixed a problem with building Netxx on Cygwin. Thanks goes to Sergio Ballestrero.
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Updated Perl scripts to work around a bug in the Perl 5.8 regex parser. Thanks goes to Andy Chou.
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Fixed a problem in the build system where Netxx could not be built on Solaris if you also wanted TLS/SSL
		    support. Thanks goes to James Sammut.
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Fixed a major bug in non-blocking connects. Thanks goes to Steve Bannister.
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Updated the build script for Mac OS X (configure.sh) so that IPv6 won't cause a problem under 10.2.
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Implemented missing copy constructor, assignment operator and swap functions for Netxx::Stream. Thanks to
		    Sebastien Bellerive for finding this one.
		</para>
	    </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <!--################################################################-->
    <section id="cl-031"><title>Version 0.3.1</title>
	<subtitle>January 13, 2003</subtitle>

	<para>
	    Version 0.3.1 is a bug fix release.
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Made some changes to the internal Netxx::ServerBase class that fixed exception safety issues and a double
		    delete[] call. Thanks to Steve Bannister for finding this.
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Made a small change to Netxx::Peer to allow Netxx to compile under MacOSX again.
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Included errno.h on windows to define EAGAIN. Thanks to Charles Kerr for the suggestion.
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    The Netxx API appendix of this manual was removed. It caused the size of the manual to be too large.
		</para>
	    </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <!--################################################################-->
    <section id="cl-030"><title>Version 0.3.0</title>
	<subtitle>November 8th, 2002</subtitle>

	<para>
	    Lots of changes, some bug fixes and some completely rewritten
	    classes. Most changes were made to make the API even easier to
	    use.
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Rewrote Address class. The address class is now independent of its actual use. No more Address::Type.
		    Auto-detection of IPv4, IPv6 and Local Domain socket addresses. Much easier to use and makes input more
		    flexible.
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Added Peer class to replace all the std::pair objects that were being used. Peer also replaces some of the
		    functionality of the old SockAddr class.
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Moved some of the classes from the public include directory into the src directory. This means that the
		    classes are no longer usable outside of Netxx. The classes are: Socket and SockAddr.
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Added a new Resolve class so that we can change the implementation of host name and service name resolution at
		    compile time based on the environment.
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    The server classes can now bind to more than one address. This allows you to either bind to all local
		    addresses or just specific ones.
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Removed the MutliServer code and replaced with a new Probe class. The new Probe class can return the readable
		    and writable state of any Netxx socket based object. Updated the multi_server example code to use the new
		    Probe class.
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Added Win32 MSVC Workspace files for compiling a Netxx static library under Win32.
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Added a shell script for building a Netxx static library under MacOS X.
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Added Netxx::TLS::Certificate class.
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Added a default passphrase function that actually works!
		</para>
	    </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <!--################################################################-->
    <section id="cl-020"><title>Version 0.2.0</title>
	<subtitle>October 22, 2001</subtitle>

	<para>
	    New features and some bug fixes.
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Fixed bug in Socket::write that shows up only when
		    write(2) returns less than the buffer size
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Fixed bug in call to select when timeout is 0
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Added TLS classes a la OpenSSL
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Moved some classes around in order to add TLS classes
		</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Added the Netxx::Netbuf class which is a IOStreams streambuf
		</para>
	    </listitem>
    
	    <listitem>
		<para>
		    Added initial support for Microsoft Windows
		</para>
	    </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <!--################################################################-->
    <section id="cl-010"><title>Version 0.1.0</title>
	<subtitle>September 7, 2001</subtitle>

	<para>
	    The Netxx code was cleaned up and moved around. The API is now
	    ready for a first release.
	</para>
    </section>
    <!--################################################################-->
    <section id="cl-000"><title>Version 0.0.0</title>
	<subtitle>March 1, 2001</subtitle>

	<para>
	    First draft of some code put together as Netxx.
	</para>
    </section>
    <!--################################################################-->
</appendix>
<!--
    vim:ft=docbk:tw=130
-->
