<?xml version="1.0"?>
<news xmlns="http://pmade.org/xmlns/project-news" xmlns:l="http://pmade.org/xmlns/project-linking">
    <entry title="Version 0.3.2 Released" year="2003" month="07" day="08">
	<para>
	    Thanks to the work of volunteers, Netxx version 0.3.2 has been
	    released. This version fixed a few major and minor bugs.
	</para>
    </entry>

    <entry title="Netxx on SourceForge" year="2003" month="04" day="08">
	<para>
	    Netxx now has a <l:ulink href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/netxx/">project page on SourceForge.net</l:ulink>.
	    Please take some time to review the site and volunteer to fix some bugs.
	</para>
    </entry>

    <entry title="Version 0.3.1 Released" year="2003" month="01" day="13">
	<para>
	    Version 0.3.1 is a bug fix release. A few exception safety
	    issues have been fixed, plus some changes for the MacOSX and
	    Win32 ports.
	</para>
    </entry>

    <entry title="Version 0.3.0 Has Been Released" year="2002" month="11" day="08">
	<para>
	    With a little over a year of work, Netxx 0.3.0 has been
	    released! This version has a lot of changes, some external, but
	    a lot of internal work. Plus TLS support is almost complete!
	</para>

	<para>
	    The API is much better now, and the code is very solid. We
	    wanted to make this release so that everyone could become
	    familiar with the new API.
	</para>
    </entry>

    <entry title="New Netxx Logo" year="2002" month="06" day="20">
	<para>
	    As part of my portfolio I have created a new logo for Netxx.
	    Also note that version 0.3.0 is in the works and it's going to
	    be very cool!
	</para>
    </entry>

    <entry title="Version 0.2 Out" year="2001" month="10" day="22">
	<para>
	    Netxx version 0.2 is out. This is still an alpha release of
	    course. I wanted to get all the new changes out although some of
	    them are not ready, like TLS on windows. Expect changes in a few
	    classes, I am going to make the library a little easier to use.
	</para>
    </entry>

    <entry title="Timeout Bug" year="2001" month="10" day="18">
	<para>
	    A bug was found in the code that calls select. It did not pass
	    select a NULL pointer for a 0 timeout. This is fixed in CVS. The
	    fix will also be in the upcoming 0.2 version.
	</para>
    </entry>

    <entry title="Windows Port Almost Done" year="2001" month="10" day="17">
	<para>
	    The Netxx port to Windows is almost complete. As soon as the
	    build system is more complete, Netxx 0.2 will be released.
	</para>
    </entry>

    <entry title="Netxx Supports TLS" year="2001" month="09" day="21">
	<para>
	    Netxx now supports TLS via OpenSSL and some wrapper classes.
	    Official Netxx TLS Release coming soon.
	</para>
    </entry>

    <entry title="Early Release Out" year="2001" month="09" day="07">
	<para>
	    An early alpha version of Netxx was released.  This is so that
	    developers can start to review the API and provide feedback.
	    This is still an alpha release that the API is subject to
	    change. With that said, it is very stable.
	</para>
    </entry>
</news>
