<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <artheader>
    <title>Programmer Guide: Dialog Usage Manager</title>
  </artheader>

<sect1> <title> Concepts </title>

<sect2> <title> Major Components </title>

<para>
The DialogUsamgeManger (or DUM) is the unit that keeps track of all the data
sturcutres and sits on top of the transaction layer of the stack. It keeps track
of multiple DialogSet which contains Dialogs. Each DialogSet contains all the
Dialog that were created by a common initial request. They all share the same
SIP Call-Id and from tag from the orginal request. Inside a specific dialogSet
there can be some type of BaseCreator that represnets the intial request that
generated the dialog. This will only exist onthe UAC side. The DialogSet also
contains serveral objects dereived from BaseUsage that are using this particular
dialog. There are several types of things that are a Usage of this dialog. There
can be one InvSession, one Registration, one Publication, multiple Subscriptions
and multiple OutOfDialogRequests. Note the name OutOfDialog is a little weird -
they are actually in a thing a lot like a dialog but are transactions that are
not in one of the other categories. Typically messages that result in
OutOfDialogRequests are MESSAGE and OPTIONS.
</para>

<para>
An initial SIP Request is created by calling the makeX interfaces on the DUM. It
is then sent using the send interface on the DUM. This will create some internal
data structures and return a DialogSetID that can be used to find all the state
asscociates resulting from this. When a response comes into this, a callback
from one of the Handler classes will be called to notify the application about
incoming events. This will pass up some type of client or server usages class
that can be used to send aditional messages and responses inthe context of this
particularr usage of the Dialog.
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2> <title> Definitions </title>

<para>
DialogUsage Manager - Main class that keeps track of all the DialogsSets,
Dialogs, and Usages.
</para> 

<para>
DialogSet - A set of dialogs that were gerneated from a common request. They
share the same call-id and the same from tag in the
request that genreated the dialog.
</para> 

<para>
Dialog - A container holding such things and local and remote CSEQ, URI,
Call-ID and such as defined by the SIP standard.
</para> 

<para>
DialogID - An identifier that uniquely finds a a Dialog by Call-ID, and to and
from tags.
</para> 
 
<para>
DialogSetID - An identifier that uniquily identifies a Dialog-Set and is formed
from Call-ID and 
</para>

<para>
Usages - These are the objects are are using a dialog. They include
ClientInviteSession, ClientOutOfDialogReq, ClientPublication,
ClientRegistration, ClientSubscription, ServerInviteSession,
ServerOutOfDialogReq, ServerPublication, ServerRegistration, and
ServerSubscription. These have varios operations that can be called on them to 
</para>

<para>
Handlers - These are objects uses to derive class from that allow callbacks from
this layer to the application using ti. They include InviteSessionHandler,
OutOfDialogHandler, RegistrationHandler, SubscribeHandler, and
PublictionHandler.
</para>

<para>
Handles - All the Usaves and Handlers are not really exposes to the
applications using this layer. Instead, handles to them are passed out. When
the applications goes to use a handle, the unerlying object may have been
delted and the applications must be prepared for this not to work.
</para> 

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1> <title>Handling Invite Sessions - Client</title>

<para>
Initially a cleint can call makeNewInvite on the DUM and get a SipMessage. It
can take this and modify it such as adding SDP. It then calls sends on the DUM
and sends themessage. This will cause the creation of a DialogSet for the
Dialogs resulting from this request. When a responses (such as a 180) comes back
that cuase the creation of an early dialog, the onEarly callback in the Handler
willbe called. This will pass in a ClientInviteSession to the applications and
the eactual message received. When and offer or answer is recived, the onAnswer
or onOffer callback will be called. In the typical case wher the INVITE sent
and offer and the 180 has SDP but it is not an answer, only the onEarly will be
called. If the 180 was reliable so that it was an aswer, then both the onEarly
and the onAnswer would be called.
</para> 

<para>
If the client which to sent a new answer or offer it must call the setAnswer or
setAnswer object with the new SDP. This saves it but does not send a
messages. the client then calls sendAnyAnswer or sendAnyOffer to cause the
aproperate message to be sent to send a new offer or answer. This might be a
PRACK, an UPDATE, a reINVITE depending on the currenst state of the dialog.
</para> 

</sect1>
<sect1> <title>Handling Invite Sessions - Server</title>
<para>
When the sserver first recives an INVITE, it will call the onNewInvSession
handler and pass a handle to a ServerInviteSession. It the UA is busy this
could be rejected with the reject mehtod. If the INVITE contaned an offer, the
onOffer callback gets called. When this happens, the server needs to call the
setAnser function to set the new offer. This will not send the offer. The
server must then call the sendAnserInAnyMessage to actually send the
offer. This sequence of two calls seem a little weired but is required to make
the all the cases work when doing PRACK stuff. 
</para>
<para>
From this pont on thir can be several rounds of sending and receivng offers and
aswers. When the UA which to sendd a 200 and "answer" the call, it calls the
accept method. Finially when it wishes to end the call it calls the end
method. If the other side ends the call, the onTerminated callback will get
called. 
</para>

<para>
INFO messages can be received in the dialog with the onInfo callback. Refer is
a topic all on it's own and covered later in this document. 
</para>

</sect1>
<sect1> <title>Handling Registration - Client</title>
<para>
The client froms a new registration message by calling makeResitration in the
DUM. This returns a SIP messages which is sent by calling send on the DUM. This
will initate the registrtionprocess. 
</para>
<para>
If it succeedes or failes, the aproperate onSuccess or onFailure will be
called. The DUM will contintue to run the times and keep this registration
alive. This may result in an onFailure callback at any time. 
</para>
<para>
The callback passes back a handle to a ClientRegistration which provies
serveral methods for the client to discover and manipulate the contacts for the
registration. myContacts refers to contatst this UA has registered while
allContacts referes to any contact that has been registered for this AOR. The
add and remove binding calls allow for manipulation of contacts this UA
registered and for cotacts that other UA registered. 
</para>

</sect1>
<sect1> <title>Handling Registrations - Server</title>
<para>
When a new registgration is received the onAdd will be called. The server needs
to either accept this on rejct it using the coresponding function isn the
ServerRegistration class. If the registration is refreshed byt the client
onRefresh will be called and if it expereis before it is refreshed, onExpired
will be called. If the client removes on of the the contacts, onRremoveOne will
be called and if the client removes all the contacts, onRemoveAll be be called.
</para>

</sect1>
<sect1> <title>Handling Subscriptions - Client</title>
<para>
</para>

</sect1>
<sect1> <title>Handling Subscritpions - Server </title>
<para>
Gets a onNewSubecritpion callabck when it is created and onRefresh or
OnTerminated as the clients updates it. 
</para>

</sect1>
<sect1> <title>Handling Publictionas - client </title>
<para>
</para>

</sect1>
<sect1> <title>Handling Publications - Server </title>
<para>
</para>

</sect1>
<sect1> <title>Dealing with Refer </title>
<para>
</para>

</sect1>
<sect1> <title>Dealing with Digest authentication </title>
<para>
</para>

</sect1>
<sect1> <title>Dealing with complex offer/answer </title>

<para>
When you receive an offer, you need to send an aswer. If you don't like
something about the SIP message with the offer you can totally reject it at the
sip level, but if you don't like the media it proposed, you need to send a
answer with all the m lines you don't like zeroed out. You can then instantly
send a counter offer to propose somethign new.
</para> 

</sect1>

</article>


